Louise Nevelson
Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution
- Photographs, circa 1903-1979, Series 9:; (Boxes 14-15, 20, OV 29; 2.3 linear feet)
  - Artist, circa 1955-1979, undated, 9.2:
    Subseries consists of photographs of Nevelson once she had become known, and began to be honored, as an artist. The majority are either portraits of the artist or photographs of the artist at work, at home, and in different settings taken by various individuals. Most notable among these are the portraits of Nevelson and photographs of her house and studio on Thirtieth Street taken by Jeremiah Russell and the photographs of Nevelson at home and in her studio, at work with her assistant Diana Mackown, and with her art work taken by Ugo Mulas, the Italian photographer known for documenting the life and work of artists. Others, including the portraits taken by Renate Ponsold and Jack Mitchell, may have been used in various art works and/or exhibitions; still others, such as the photographs taken by Basil Langton, may have been intended for publication. Also found are photographs of Nevelson at various exhibitions and openings (including the opening of her show at Studio Marconi in Milan, Italy), at various social gatherings (including a reception at her brother's hotel, the Thorndike Hotel, where she was photographed with Andrew Wyeth), and receiving various awards and honors (including honorary degrees from Columbia University and Smith College, and the first Women's Caucus for Art Award). Also included are photographs from the artist, Robert Indiana, featuring himself in front of his and Nevelson's sculptures, and at gatherings with Nevelson, and some photographs that were featured in Look magazine.
    Photographs are arranged into files according to photographer, type, or subject. Files are arranged in rough chronological order.
    - Portrait by Jeremiah Russell, circa 1955, (See also Box 20 and OV 29; not scanned in entirety) (Box 14, Folder 7)
    - Photographs of Louise Nevelson's House and Studio on Thirtieth Street by Jeremiah Russell, circa 1955 (Box 14, Folder 8)
    - Photographs of Louise Nevelson (negatives without prints), 1950s, (Not scanned) (Box 14, Folder 9)
    - Photographs of Louise Nevelson, 1964-1975, undated, (3 folders; see also Box 20 and OV 29) (Box 14, Folder 10-12)
    - Photographs of Louise Nevelson by Ugo Mulas, circa 1965, (3 folders; see also Box 20) (Box 14, Folder 13-15)
    - Photographs of Louise Nevelson at Various Exhibitions and Openings, 1960s-1970s, (4 folders) (Box 14, Folder 16-19)
    - Portraits, 1960s-1970s, (See also Box 20) (Box 14, Folder 20)
      Includes ones by Marie Cosindas, Jack Mitchell, and others.
    - Photographs of Louise Nevelson at Various Gatherings, 1969-1970s, (2 folders) (Box 14, Folder 21-22)
    - Photographs from Robert Indiana, 1971, 1973, (3 folders) (Box 14, Folder 23-25)
    - Photographs of Louise Nevelson Receiving Various Awards and Honors, 1970s, (2 folders) (Box 14, Folder 26-27)
    - Portraits, Self-Portrait, and Art Work Photograph by Arnie Zane, 1974 (Box 14, Folder 28)
    - Portraits by Renate Ponsold, 1979 (Box 14, Folder 29)
    - Photographs of Louise Nevelson by Basil Langton, undated (Box 14, Folder 30)
    - Photographs of Louise Nevelson for Look Magazine, undated (Box 14, Folder 31)
    - Miscellaneous Photographs (relating to but not featuring Nevelson), undated (Box 14, Folder 32)
    - Oversize, Photographs of Louise Nevelson, 1964-1975, undated, (See Box 14, F10-12) (Box 20 (sol))
    - Oversize, Photographs of Louise Nevelson by Ugo Mulas, circa 1965, (See Box 14, F13-15) (Box 20 (sol))
    - Oversize, Portraits, 1960s-1970s, (See Box 14, F20) (Box 20 (sol))
    - Oversize, Portrait by Jeremiah Russell, circa 1955, (See Box 14, F7) (Box OV 29)
    - Oversize, Photographs of Louise Nevelson, 1964-1975, undated, (See Box 14, F10-12) (Box OV 29)
  - Exhibitions and Installations, 1959-1979, 9.3:
    Subseries consists of photographs of Nevelson's art work in various exhibitions and on display in various locations. Included are photographs of an exhibition at the Martha Jackson Gallery (October-November, 1959) and of a retrospective at the Whitney Museum in 1979, as well as of a Nevelson work on display at the Tate Gallery; and a photograph album of her one-man show at the Minami Gallery, Tokyo, Japan in 1975. Other photographs include ones of Nevelson's work displayed in the Thorndike Hotel (owned by her brother) and the Queens College library; and ones of Nevelson's outdoor (metal) sculptures installed at Wichita State University, Yale University, and in Italy, as well as ones of a Nevelson wood sculpture in an outdoor setting (not necessarily an outdoor sculpture).
    Files are arranged in chronological order.
    - Exhibition at Martha Jackson Gallery, 1959 (Box 14, Folder 33)
    - Nevelson Work in the Tate Gallery, 1965 (Box 14, Folder 34)
    - Various and Unidentified Exhibitions,1960s (Box 14, Folder 35)
    - Indoor Installations and Displays, circa 1960s-1970s (Box 14, Folder 36)
    - Outdoor Installation and Displays, 1970s, (See also Box 20) (Box 14, Folder 37)
    - Photograph Album, Exhibition at Minami Gallery (Tokyo, Japan), 1975, (See Box 20) (Box 14, Folder 38)
    - Retrospective at the Whitney Museum, 1979 (Box 14, Folder 39)
    - Oversize, Outdoor Installations and Displays, circa 1970s, (See Box 14, F37) (Box 20 (sol))
    - Oversize, Photograph Album, Exhibition at Minami Gallery (Tokyo, Japan), 1975, (See Box 14, F38) (Box 20 (sol))
  - Art Work, 1940s-1970s, 9.4:
    Subseries consists of photographs of Nevelson's art work (primarily works in terra cotta, tattistone, and wood, as well as some drawings and paintings). Also included are scattered photographs of paintings by Louis Eilshemius (amongst the ones taken by John Schiff and Jeremiah Russell) and Ralph Rosenborg that Nevelson owned. At least some of the photographs by Schiff seem to have been created for the Nierendorf Gallery; photographs by Russell were likely created for Nevelson; photographs by Buckley Semley, Oliver Baker, and Rudy Burckhardt seem to have been created for the Martha Jackson Gallery (some of these, especially the ones by Semley, may have been used in the inventory of Nevelson's art work carried out by her assistants and gallery staff). Photographs of Nevelson's art work are typically undated, most lack any identifying information, and many are duplicates. Numbers on the verso of some seem to correspond to the art work pictured, however there is no further information about what exactly the number is meant to reference or signify.
    Photographs are arranged in files according to photographer. Photographs of various works, art work by Ralph Rosenborg, and unidentified art work are arranged in separate files at the end of the series. Even though most photographs are undated, dates provided represent the decade in which the photographs were most likely created. Files are arranged in rough chronological order.
    - Photographs by John Schiff, 1940s, (3 folders; not scanned) (Box 14, Folder 40-42)
    - Photographs by Jeremiah Russell, 1950s, (8 folders; not scanned) (Box 14, Folder 43-50)
    - Photographs by Jeremiah Russell, Negatives, 1950s, (3 folders; not scanned) (Box 14, Folder 51-53)
    - Photographs by Jeremiah Russell, Negatives, 1950s, (4 folders; not scanned) (Box 15, Folder 1-4)
    - Photographs by Buckley Semley, 1950s, (7 folders; not scanned) (Box 15, Folder 5-11)
    - Photographs by Oliver Baker, late 1950s, (2 folders; not scanned) (Box 15, Folder 12-13)
    - Photographs by Rudy Burckhardt, late 1950s, (4 folders; not scanned) (Box 15, Folder 14-17)
    - Photographs by Tom Kendall, late 1950s, (Not scanned) (Box 15, Folder 18)
    - Various Nevelson Works of Art, 1950s-1970s, (2 folders; not scanned) (Box 15, Folder 19-20)
    - Various Nevelson Works of Art (negatives), undated, (Not scanned) (Box 15, Folder 21)
    - Works of Art by Ralph Rosenborg, undated, (Not scanned) (Box 15, Folder 22)
    - Unidentified Art Work, undated, (Not scanned) (Box 15, Folder 23)
  - Slides, 1950s-1970s, 9.5:
    Subseries consists of glass slides and transparencies of Nevelson and her art work. The photographs on these slides typically do not duplicate those found amongst the artist and art work photographs above. Included are glass slides of photographs taken by Dorothy Dehner, primarily documenting the works of art in the rooms, studio, and garden of Nevelson's house on Thirtieth Street. Dehner's photographs also feature Nevelson at work and posed in front of certain works, outside views of the house, and the Eilshemius paintings and pre-Columbian sculptures owned by Nevelson. Dehner took the photographs on successive trips to Nevelson's house. The slides appear to be numbered in various sequences, perhaps corresponding to each trip. However, at this point, all the slides have been mixed together and it is difficult to reconstruct any meaningful order from the numbers.
    Also included are various slides of Nevelson and her art work dating from the 1950s; slides of art work dating from circa 1961, three of which seem to have been used by Tom Kendall in a lecture; slides of Nevelson and her assistant in front of her house, and ones of Nevelson alone in her house and studio dating from the mid-1960s; slides featuring Nevelson posing in front of her art work, at home and in her studio, in her neighborhood, and at a foundry, and slides featuring different views of various outdoor installations of her metal sculptures, all of which date from the 1970s; and glass slides of Nevelson art work, along with some negatives.
    Slides are undated; however the dates provided represent the decade in which they were most likely created. Slides are arranged according to type and photographer or subject of photograph.
    - Glass Slides of Photographs by Dorothy Dehner, circa 1956, (See also Box 16; not scanned) (Box 15, Folder 24)
    - Slides of Artist and Art Work Photographs, 1950s, (Not scanned) (Box 15, Folder 25)
    - Slides of Art Work Photographs, circa 1961, (Not scanned) (Box 15, Folder 26)
    - Slides of Artist Photographs, 1964, (Not scanned) (Box 15, Folder 27)
    - Slides of Artist and Installation Photographs, 1970s, (Not scanned) (Box 15, Folder 28)
    - Miscellaneous Glass Slides of Art Work Photographs, undated, (2 folders; see also Box 16; not scanned) (Box 15, Folder 29-30)
    - Copy Prints and Negatives Made by AAA, undated, (2 folders; not scanned) (Box 15, Folder 31-32)
    - Glass Slides of Photographs by Dorothy Dehner, circa 1956, (See Box 15, F24; not scanned) (Box 16 (hol))
    - Miscellaneous Glass Slides of Art Work Photographs, undated, (Not scanned) (Box 16 (hol))
Index to Notable Correspondents from Series 2: Correspondence
List represents only a selection of correspondents and does not include names of family.
Albright-Knox Art Gallery: 1971
American Federation of Arts: 1961, 1964
American Women in Radio and Television: 1959
Art in America: 1963, 1965
Art Institute of Chicago: 1962
The Artists' Gallery: 1955
Bloch, Ernest: 1933
Bourgeois, Louise: undated
Bowdoin College: 1971
Brandeis University: 1971
Brooklyn Museum: 1956
Brooklyn Society of Artists: 1957
Buffalo Fine Arts Academy: 1962
Calder, Sandy: 1955
Chatham College: 1971
City of Scottsdale, Arizona: 1973
Cleveland Museum of Art: 1977
Colby College: 1957, 1973
Contemporary Arts Association of Houston: 1953
Cordier, Daniel: 1961
Dallas Museum of Fine Arts: 1974
Dehner, Dorothy: 1960
Detroit Institute of the Arts: 1966
Dord Fitz School and Gallery: 1960
Feininger, Lyonel: 1955
Galerie Jeanne-Bucher: 1961
Genauer, Emily: 1955
Grand Central Art Galleries: 1959
Guggenheim, Peggy: 1946
Hamline University: 1970, 1971
Harry Salpeter Gallery: 1961
Hirschhorn, Joseph: 1968
Hobart and William Smith Colleges: 1971
Indiana, Robert: 1966
Jackson, Martha (See Martha Jackson Gallery)
Jacobi, Lotte: 1960, 1963, 1965
Kendall, Tom: 1959, 1961, undated
Knox, Seymour: 1968
Kramer, Hilton: 1957
Lipman, Howard: 1962
Lipton, Seymour: 1955
Mademoiselle: 1961, 1962
Martha Jackson Gallery: 1956, 1959, 1960, 1961, 1962, 1967, 1968, undated
Massachusetts Institute of Technology, Center for Advanced Visual Studies: 1971
Miller, Kenneth Hayes: 1931, 1933
Milone, Joe: 1941
Minneapolios College of Art and Design: 1971
Mount Holyoke College: 1962, 1964
Museum of Art, Carnegie Institution: 1967, 1971, 1974
Museum of Fine Arts of Houston: 1954
Museum of Modern Art: 1943, 1953, 1955, 1964, 1967, 1968
National Association of Women Artists: 1953, 1954
National Foundation on the Arts and Humanities: 1966
Neumann, Hans: 1962
Neumann, J. B.: 1954
New School for Social Research: 1961
The New York Times: 1968
New York State Council on the Arts: 1968
The New Yorker: 1967
Newsweek: 1967
Nierenforf, Karl: 1941, 1943, 1946
Nordjyllands Kunstmuseum: 1973
Ono, Yoko: 1971
Pace Gallery: 1976
Pennsylvania Academy of Fine Arts: 1952, 1970
Philadelphia College of Art: 1961, 1968
Philadelphia Museum of Art: 1965
Princeton University: 1962
Queens College: 1958
Rhode Island School of Design: 1971
Riverside Museum: 1964
Rockefeller, Nelson: 1960, 1962, 1966, 1968
Roberts, Collette: 1952, 1953
Robus, Hugo: 1958
Rosenblum, Robert: 1958
Sewall, Mrs. Sumner: 1943
Silvermine Guild of Artists: 1953, 1954, 1955
Skowhegan School of Painting and Sculpture: 1970, 1971
Solomon R. Guggenheim Museum: 1964, 1966
Tamarind Lithography Work Shop: 1971
Tate Gallery: 1963, 1966, 1967, 1968
Teachers College, Columbia University: 1964
Trenton State College: 1961
Tyler, Parker: 1958
United States Committee of the International Association of Art: 1971
University of Alabama, Department of Art: 1964
University of Bridgeport: 1971
University of Nebraska Art Galleries: 1951
Vogue: 1964
Wadsworth Atheneum Museum of Art: 1962
Walker Art Center: 1971, 1973
Weber, Max: 1947, 1948, 1950, 1951
Western College for Women: 1964
The White House: 1974
Whitney Museum of American Art: 1950, 1956, 1957, 1962, 1964, 1966, 1967
Wichita State University: 1974
The Woman's College of The University of North Carolina: 1951
Women's Interart Center: 1973
Yale University, Department of Art: 1961